Maybe just started the משנה Mishnah real fast as a review. From
back there? We're going to start the משנה Mishnah back there. Okay,
this is בבא מציעא Bava Metzia ק"ה kuf hey 105 and we're
starting at the bottom of 104b, we're in the middle of a
discussion about עיסקא. iska. What עיסקא iska is, is it's a way
of giving somebody a loan and getting interest back
without actually
getting interest
back
because of course you can't get interest. So what it does is
that
I give somebody stuff, it's sort of treated as two halves. One
half is a פיקדון, pikadon, one half is in my guardianship, it's
not mine, it belongs to the lender, and half of it is
just a loan. So it's as if it's my money. I go
out and I spend it to try to make a profit. And
then if what occurs is that I lose some of it, we
split the losses half and half, so it's an equal partnership in
terms of loss. Then in order that it not even look like
interest, when I, if I make a profit, I actually get two-thirds
of the profit and the person who loaned me the money only
gets a third. Now, there are two ways of doing this, as
רבא Rava is about to say at the bottom of 104b. One
way is that we can sort of treat the two halves entirely
separately, the פיקדון pikadon half, or we can treat it as two
halves. And depending on what happens to each half, there's a different,
it's worse or better for the מלווה malveh or the לווה. loveh.
אמר רבא: חדא עיסקא ותרי שטרי פסידא דמלווה, תרי עיסקי וחד שטרא
פסידא דלווה. Amara Rava: chada iska u-trei shtarei psida d'malveh, trei iskei
v-chad shtara psida d'loveh. So that's really vague. And רש"י Rashi has
to go out of his way here, many, many lines of רש"י
Rashi to explain what in the world we're talking about. So I'm
going to try to do that without looking at רש"י Rashi to
see if I remember what it is, but I do. Okay. So
if we have one עיסקא iska and תרי שטרי. trei shtarei. So
it's one thing and I have two entirely separate halves. And half
A I have minus, I lose five dollars on. And on half
B I gain fifteen dollars. Nice if I'd written black, but I
don't. And it's okay. So then we treat because of תרי שטרי,
trei shtarei, we treat the two halves entirely separately. Even though it's
one עיסקא, iska, you would think it's like okay, you loan me
this and I lost on this part which went into that market,
I lost five, and this part which went into the other market
I gained fifteen. So you think we'd join them? No, תרי שטרי,
trei shtarei, we treat them separately. So here we split the losses
and the מלווה malveh gets minus two and a half and the
לווה loveh gets minus two and a half. So we split the
losses between the lender and the lesser, I can never remember which
one is which, the lender and the debtor.
Here it's one-third and two-thirds. So it's minus, it's plus five to
the lender. Why is it one-third and two-thirds? Because that's how an
עיסקא iska works. That's just what an עיסקא iska is, is that
it's one-third, we share the profits a third, two-thirds so that it's
not מחזי כריבית, mechzei k'ribbit, it doesn't look like ריבית ribbit and
we split the losses half and half because that's the deal.
This is a תקנה של חכמים takanah shel chachamim that they made
this rule that you can do this thing to give money to
help, you can give money as a loan with interest without it
being a loan at interest.
And it's plus ten to the לווה. loveh.
So that's
פסידא דמלווה. psida d'malveh. פסידא דמלווה Psida d'malveh he says, because if
we put together the minus two point five and the plus five,
the lender only gets back two point five in profit. Even though
if we treated it... But
he also, he also gets that plus five or whatever. The plus
five comes out net plus two point five. So the net gain
to the מלווה malveh when we had, when we separated it into
two parts was only two point five as opposed to if we
have תרי עיסקי וחד שטרא. trei iskei v-chad shtara. This was minus
five and this was plus fifteen. We put them together because it's
חד שטרא. chad shtara. That's plus ten and we get plus three
point three to the מלווה malveh and six point six six
to the לווה. loveh. So the person who lent the money comes
out better when all that I give goes together.
And so that's just what רבא Rava is saying here.
Does it have to be two-thirds, one-third? Could it just be a
loan that's fifty-fifty? Could it be one forty-nine? I think it has
to be minimally two-thirds, one-third. That's what seems to come out of
the גמרא Gemara here. What was the difference in the second case?
It
was, I don't mean the numbers, I mean what was the case
because that was... So in the first case it's חדא עיסקא. chada
iska. I have one bundle of stuff. עיסקא Iska means what's the
word?
It's business... a business deal. of a venture, it's like in modern
Hebrew it means a deal. Here it means something that I loan
to you which is half... which is half in your guardianship and
half loan. Okay, so it's money, it's stuff. I think רש״י Rashi
has a חבילות של בגדים. chabilot shel bgadim. חבילה של בגדים chavila
shel bgadim so it's a bunch of textiles that I'm selling, bunch
of clothing that I'm selling. So it's stuff, it's widgets. I give
you a box of widgets,
but because you're going to sell half of it in Nehardea and
half of it in Pumbedita, it's תרי שטרי. trei shtari.
שטר Shtar one and שטר shtar two
and then each of those is treated separately to the detriment of
the lender as we saw, he only gets net plus 2.5 even
though if it were one שטר shtar that I gave you two
חבילות, chabilot, one was going to go to Nehardea and one was
going to go to Pumbedita, but I'm treating them as one lease,
one contract... guardianship... one contract, then it's better for the lender. Yeah.
Why is that a loan at all? It's not. It's a business
deal, it's not a loan. Half of it is sort of a
loan, but the point is that under the terms of this agreement,
even though it's... I can't pay you back interest. But under the
terms of the way this agreement works, when I make a profit,
I give you a third of the profit, which is sort of
like... you still have to pay back the original... Yes, yes, you
give the קרן, keren, you give the principal of the loan.
On both... on both pieces here it means something different from the
two halves of an עיסקא. iska. An עיסקא iska has two halves
in that half of it is yours and half of it is
mine, and then here we're talking about a different issue where the
עיסקא iska is of two parts, two physical things that I give
you, which is why רש״י Rashi is not talking about כסף, kesef,
he's not talking about money, he's talking about stuff, clothing. Yeah, he
says שפמטיא, safmatya, you know, merchandise. I go... I'm like the... let's
say you have a great idea, you have no funding, right? I
provide you with the funding, you do all the work, but in
return we split the profit. But we don't want it to be
100 percent... we don't want it to be like 50/50 per se
because then you have the whole idea of... it looks like... it
looks like lending at interest. Right. We split the profit disproportionately,
but I still have to give you back for losses. But, you
know, in order for it not to seem like ריבית, ribit, therefore
although the losses may be split evenly, the profit won't be. So
it won't be entirely... right... you get a better deal out of
it. If we were splitting profits equally in this case, that would
be מחזי כריבית. mechezi k'ribit. It would look like I was loaning
at interest, and I can't loan at interest, and I can't look
like I'm loaning at interest. So there's a thing called עיסקא, iska,
which is just below the level of looking like lending at interest
that it's okay.
And one of the things about it is that you can either
split it into sort of two contracts or you can put it
as one contract,
and that has implications for if something is... that has implications for
who's going to come out better, or everyone's going to come out
better in this case, but how much better.
I would think in order for it not to be מחזי כריבית,
mechezi k'ribit, it would be like less than a... just something like
that. Like a big thing like a third and two thirds, that's
like a large quantity. That's what I was wondering. That's all. There's
not much to say about it. כך תקנו חכמים. Kach tiknu chachamim.
This is how they made it. Alright, good answer. Okay, it's a
bad answer but that's the only answer I have. Okay, רבא Rava
has a few more things to say about עיסקא iska before we
move on to the next משנה. mishna. ואימר רבא? V'eimar Rava? Now
we're on the first line of the top of ק״ה עמוד א.
qof hey amud aleph. האי מאן דקביל עיסקא מחבריה ופסיד טרח ומלאיה
ולא אודעיה לא מצי אמר ליה דרי מהך פסידא בהדאי. Hai man
d'kabel iska m'chavrei upaseid tarach umalya v'lo odyeih lo matzi amar lei
dari mehach psida bahadai. משום דאמר ליה בהכי טרחת למלוותיה כי היכי
דלא ליקרו לך מפסדי עיסקא. Mishum d'amar lei bahachi taracht l'malyotei ki
heichi d'lo likru lach mafsidei iska. So if
a person gets an עיסקא, iska, this sort of package deal investment
thing,
from his friend and he loses money on it, and but then
he goes back and he works hard and he says, you know
what? I'm not done with this. The terms of the agreement aren't
over. I'm going to go back and I'm going to get this
money back. And he gets the money back. He can't then go
and say, you know, I lost, split the losses me with... I
was losing out a month ago. Split the losses with me from
the point that I lost.
Probably it was before the term of the agreement if that was
the case. I can't say with me come and split with me
from the term... from the point that I lost, because the original
lender can say back to you, no, you went and worked back
to get back the principal because you didn't want to be called
somebody who fails on business ventures, who loses an עיסקא, iska, who
loses עיסקא. iska. So they both... so I have a bad argument
for why you should split the losses with me, even though that's
the term of the agreement,
because I went and worked back to get the principal back. So
in the end I have to just pay... we just have to...
I have to give you the principal even though I didn't make
any profit. What are we trying to say? We say we just
abide by the original terms? What are the...
There was a point, there was a point at which I lost,
I was losing money and I would have had to split losses
with you. Yeah. And I would have lost my two dollar, my
twenty thousand dollars
out of the forty thousand dollar loss let's say. I can't. And
then I work and I say no, no, no, give me some
more time. I can't say, okay, I got the twenty thousand dollars
back and we're back to square one, split the losses with me
that I had a month ago. Oh, okay. Right, no, because it's
a separate venture in a way. This is a separate venture in
a way. It's a separate... No, what he's trying to say is
the original venture. The original venture. That's the point. That's the point.
You can't retrospectively say if I stopped here I would have... Okay,
yeah. And the language of תחלומי מלייא Tachlumei malya is gonna make
it up like למילייא. Lemalya. Yeah. Okay. Okay. Another point of רבא
Rava is a more interesting one, which is now we have a
partnership venture where two gu- two people are coming together and they're
getting an investment, an עיסקא Iska investment from a third party.
הני בי תרי דעבדי עיסקא בהדי הדדי ורווח. Hani bei trei de-avdi
iska be-hadei hadada ve-ravach. And then they make a profit, רווח. Revach.
ואמר ליה חד לחבריה לא פלוג. Ve-amar lei chad le-chaverei lo pelog.
And the one says,
okay, I'm done.
What does it mean by he says I'm done? אי אמר ליה,
Ei amar lei, these are three different version- three different things that
he could say. אי אמר ליה אידך נרווח טפי דינו הוא דמעכב.
Ei amar lei idach narvach tfei dino hu de-me'akev. Oh, sorry, that's
the whole point, that's the דין. Din. If the other one says,
no, I'm not... we still have time on it, I want to
make more profit, I can stop you from ending here. Or I
can stop you from splitting away. Now, what does it mean to
split away? ואי אמר ליה הב לי פלגא
דרווחא. Ve-ei amar lei hav li plaga de-ravcha. Do things not have
a term, like these go on forever? I assume they have a
term. This is treated more extensively in איזהו נשך, Eizehu Neshech, which
is in ס''ו ס''ח. Samech vav samech chet.
I don't remember when it ends. Well, me neither.
I actually don't know. Okay. So, sorry, the דין, Din, the main
basic rule is אמר רבא הני בי תרי דעבדי עיסקא בהדי הדדי
ורווח ואמר ליה חד לחבריה לא פלוג ואי אמר ליה אידך נרווח
טפי דינו הוא דמעכב. Amar Rava hani bei trei de-avdi iska be-hadei
hadada ve-ravach ve-amar lei chad le-chaverei lo pelog ve-ei amar lei idach
narvach tfei dino hu de-me'akev. That either one can... that I can
stop you from splitting off the עיסקא Iska just because we had
profit at this point. So you can't do... it's not a buy-out,
it's splitting off. ואי אמר ליה הב לי
פלגא דרווחא. Ve-ei amar lei hav li plaga de-ravcha. If the guy
who's done says give me half the profit because I'm not interested
in doing this work anymore,
אמר ליה, Amar lei, the argument he has back, רווחא לקרנא משתעבד.
Ravcha le-karna mishtabed. No,
there's essentially a lien on the profit we make by the principal,
so that if we were to go forward or let's say you
want to be done but I'm not done, the profit that we
make together on this one עיסקא Iska that we both contracted for,
the profit is there to fill up any loss in the principal
that should occur in the future. And so you can't say give
me half the profit, I need that half the profit in case
the business venture should go south. Until when? Until the end of
the period. At the
start it must be stipulated... the one guy wants out early, he's
done really well, he wants to buy out. There is a... half
of the עיסקא Iska is a loan, so there has to be
an end point to the loan. It's at least a month and
then it could be more. It could be less than a month,
but סתם Stam it's a month. What if they both decide they
want out even though it's before the end, can they do that?
Yes, they can pay back the loan. It's only
if one guy wants out. And could you also put a mo-
you know in the original agreement in terms of if one person
wants out before the period's over? Yeah, you can, I think you
can certainly make a תנאי. Tnai. I think you can always make
a condition, and this one is without condition. Okay.
That is what I assume to be the case. It's like, you
know, when you do an investment fund you say it's like a
five-year hold, right? Let's say you want out early, and the other
guy says, no, you know, it's suppose to be five years, I
can make more money, you know, it's... Yeah, what do you do?
You do this? You do this. Or you have to maybe have
to pay something extra for getting out early or something like that.
You have to leave the... stipulated contractual period, you know, one person
has to hold it through to the end. Well, actually so at
the end of this סוגיא Sugya it's not clear that he can
get out of it at all unless it was unless it was
contracted as such, so let's get there and then see what it
says.
ואי
אמר ליה הב לי פלגא דרווחא ופלגא דקרנא. Ve-ei amar lei hav
li plaga de-ravcha u-plaga de-karna. No, fine, I understand that the profit
is connected to the principal, so that if you should lose in
the future, fine, so split the principal with me too and you'll
go on your own and I'll go on mine. אמר ליה עיסקא
דהדדי משתעבד. Amar lei iska de-hadada mishtabed. No, these are together, what
are you talking about? ואי אמרת ליה נפלוג רווחא ונפלוג קרנא... Ve-ei
amart lei niflog ravcha ve-niflog karna... Okay,
fine, ואי
מטי לך פסידא דרינא בהדך. Ve-ei mati lach pseida dareina behadach. Now,
okay, fine, I understand they're dependent on one another and so if
this part of the עיסקא Iska fails then
this part of the principal goes south because you went over there
and you dealt with it and הדדי... hadada... and I'm with you
then my... My profit has to cover your loss of the principal.
And if I lose out on my principal then you have to
pay out of your profit. That’s fine, I understand.
We’ll go our separate ways, I’ll cover you in terms of losses,
I just don’t want to do this anymore. אמר ליה *amar lei*,
אי אמר ליה מזלא דבי תרי עדיף *ee amar lei mazla d’bei
trei adif*. No, it’s better for us to work together. They’re not
saying that, it’s literally saying that, like, sort of our luck is
better when you’re working in a partnership
than separately.
And so, at the end of the day you can’t split unless
it was stipulated before. תוספות Tosafot *Tosfot* point out here that if
at the end of the day you can argue מזלא דבי תרי
עדיף *mazla d’bei trei adif*, you can’t leave, it’s better off in
partnership than it is alone, is sort of just a winning argument
no matter what. But the other ones are better arguments, that this
is the way an עיסקא *iska* works is that firstly, קרנא משעבד
לקרנא *karna meshubad l’karna* is that רווחא משעבד לקרנא *revacha meshubad l’karna*
that the profits are, there’s a lien on the profits by the
principal, that you have to have that there to make it up
and they’re dependent on one another. If you split the עיסקא *iska*
into two parts then if there’s a loss in part of the
principal in one half then it’s covered by the profit in the
other half. So those are, those are stronger arguments than our business
luck is better when we’re together even though it still works at
the end of the day. It’s a psychological argument, מזלא דבי תרי
עדיף *mazla d’bei trei adif*. מזלא דבי תרי *mazla d’bei trei*, I
don’t think that’s a psychological argument. It’s מזלא *mazla*. No, it’s saying
מזלא *mazla*, he’s talking about מזלא *mazla*, that’s astrological.
You want it to mean something else because this person means something
non-psychological.
Okay fine, I’ll let it go.
Wait, what do you mean by astrological? Astrological
is the מזלא *mazla*, the stars, the planets are going to be
lined up with us better if we stick together. So it’s not
a rule forever, it’s just like our עיסקא *iska* was exactly when
the sun... No, I said I would... So the way I would
think about this if I were to think is that you have
one person and their מזלא *mazla* is bad right now, okay, everything
is going to go south. If you have two people and their
מזלא *mazla*, a little bit good, a little bit bad, it evens
out.
Or you’re a Scorpio, you’re a Capricorn, the מזלא *mazla* Scorpio’s not
so good today but you’re a Capricorn. Or it’s the מזלא *mazla*
of two people together, it’s hard, it’s like they don’t really cooperate
and so we have sort of more work, we can do more
work if we’re sort of affected by two things because they don’t
sort of interact properly. I don’t know exactly what it means but
it doesn’t mean anything psychological in its פשט *pshat*. I’m sorry.
Two are better than one, you know, in טובים השנים מן האחד
*tovim ha’shenayim min ha’echad*. Okay. The next section, המקבל שדה מחבירו hamakabel
sadeh mechavero ולא רצה לנכש ואמר לו מה אכפת לך הואיל ואני
נותן לך חכירך אין שומעין לו מפני שיכול לומר לו למחר אתה
יוצא ממנה ומעלה לפני עשבים *ha’mekabel sade me’chavero v’lo ratza lenakesh ve’amar
lo mah ichpat lach ho’il va’ani noten lach chakirkah ein shom’in lo
mipnei she’yakhol lomar lo le’machar atah yotze mimena u’malah lefanai asavim*. It’s
a משנה mishnah. *mishna*. רש"י Rashi *Rashi* points out that even though
this is using לשון lashon מקבל *lashon mekabel*, we’re talking about קבלנות
kablanut *kablanut*, which somebody, it looks like we’re talking about קבלנות *kablanut*,
which is somebody who’s leasing a field on agreement to give a
portion of its produce to the owner, it’s actually, this one has
to be talking about חכרנות *chakranut*, which is somebody who’s leased it
at a fixed payment, there’s a set amount, 100 סאה se'ah *se’ah*
for example, which is probably far too much in reality. It just
says that, חכירך *chakirkah* later. Right, so that’s exactly what we’re pointing
out is that even though it says מקבל *mekabel*, לשון lashon מקבל
*lashon mekabel* can work both for קבלנות *kablanut* and חכירות *chakirut*. Anyway,
so if I lease the field at agreement to pay a fixed
amount but I don’t want to weed the field, and it sounds
like I should be able to say מה אכפת לך *mah ichpat
lach*, what does it matter to you? הואיל ואני נותן לך *ho’il
va’ani noten lach*, I’m giving you your lease, I’m giving you your
rent. אין שומעין לו *ein shom’in lo*, that’s not a good argument.
מפני שיכול לומר לו למחר אתה יוצא ממנה ומעלה לפני עשבים *mipnei
she’yakhol lomar lo le’machar atah yotze mimena u’malah lefanai asavim*. You’re depreciating
the property, you can leave and you’re depreciating the property. You’ve left
my field full of weeds and I don’t want that. You said
you would work the field, and we’re going to deal more with
what does it mean to work the field,
and you can work the field. אי אמר ליה *ee amar lei*,
says the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*, אי אמר ליה לבתר הכי כרבנא לה
*ee amar lei l’vatar hachi krevna lah*. Okay, fine, I understand. I’m
going to, but I’ll plow the field after the planting season. אמר
ליה חטי מעליאתא בעינא *amar lei chitei ma’alyata ba’ina*. No, I want
you to weed it now because I want good, I want good
wheat at the end of the day.
And so saying I’ll plow it later, I’ll deal, I’ll do some
version of ניכוש *nikush*, I’ll do some version of weeding later on
in the season and you’ll have your field, I’m not leaving yet,
I just don’t want to do this right now. He says, no,
I want good wheat. ואי אמר ליה זבנא לך חטי מן שוקא
*ve’ee amar lei
zivna lach chitei min shuka*. Fine, I’ll buy you wheat from the
שוק *shuk*. He can argue back, אמר ליה חטי דארעא בעינא *amar
lei chitei d’ara ba’ina*. No, I want the wheat from my field.
I don’t have a field for fun, I have a field because
I like the wheat that grows in my field. ואי אמר ליה
אנכש לך שיעור shiur מנתך *ve’ee amar lei anakesh lach shiur m’natakh*.
Fine, I’ll weed the amount of space on the field that it
takes to get... the amount that I owe you in wheat from
your field. Fine.
אמר
ליה כמנצבא דשימרא לעראי. kamantzeva deshimra le'arai. No, I don't care if
it's- I don't care if you're going to fix it later. I
don't care if what you're going to do now. If you leave
part of my field
improperly worked, you're giving it a bad name and I don't want
you to do that. You said you would take good care of
this field and you're not- and you're not properly taking care of
this field and you have to.
והתנן vehatnan okay, so we have all these arguments, but the mishnah
said that there's one in- one argument in particular that it's
התנן hatnan מפני שמלטל לפני העשבים. mipnei shemefaltel lifnei ha'asavim. You're leaving
my field bad. What are we talking about שמרא? shemra? אלא משום
דאמר ליה ela mishum de'amar lei ברזא דנפל נפל. barza denafal nafal.
Really what's going on here is we're talking about once you've started
the pro- once
you've-
once you've taken the- the חבית havit
the barrel, the barrel of wine, once the faucet has fallen out,
it's fallen out, you can't put it back. You've already lost, a
loss is a loss and these are all the same.
המקבל שדה מחבירו new משנה. mishnah. Have we read this already? Yes.
Yeah, because I was trying to figure out what that means. The
note is that- yeah, but like in other words like once the-
once there's a weed, you know, it's going to spawn more. Right,
the way רש״י Rashi explains it is like, okay, you might say
מלטל לפני העשבים mefaltel lifnei ha'asavim is like you can't say מלטל
לפני העשבים mefaltel lifnei ha'asavim is all of these things because it's
once you've now refused to weed the field, even if you do-
even if you weed a little bit of it but you leave
part of it unweeded and you're just going to plow it later
to uproot those weeds, those weeds are there, they're in the field
and they're going to regrow next year. Next year is what matters
to me, not this year. ברזא דנפל נפל. barza denafal nafal. By
not doing the work properly now, you're ruining it in the future.
And that's what it means מלטל לפני העשבים mefaltel lifnei ha'asavim is-
is a perpetual- yes, it's a- you've done this, that's a big
problem. You have not taken proper care of the field.
Now we'll do the משנה. mishnah. המקבל שדה מחבירו ולא עשתה אם
יש בה כדי להעמיד כרי חייב לטפל בה. hamakabel sadeh mechavero velo
asatah im yesh bah kedei le'amid kari chayav letapel bah. If I
rent a field, someone- one person rents a field from another but
it doesn't produce. אם יש בה כדי להעמיד כרי im yesh bah
kedei le'amid kari if it has enough to make a stack, you
still have to work- חייב לטפל בה. chayav letapel bah. אמר רבי
יהודה מה קצבה כרי? amar Rabbi Yehudah mah kitzvah kari? What are
we talking about a כרי? kari? אלא אם
יש בה כדי נפילה. ela im yesh bah kedei nefilah. If it's
producing enough that it should have- that it produces enough seed to
re-seed it the next year.
And that's our משנה. mishnah. תנו רבנן. tanu rabanan. ברייתא. braita. המקבל
שדה מחבירו ולא עשתה אם יש בה כדי להעמיד כרי חייב לטפל
בה. hamakabel sadeh mechavero velo asatah im yesh bah kedei le'amid kari
chayav letapel bah. So it's a version of the משנה. Mishna, שכך
כותב לו shekach kotev lo because that's the לשון that- that's the
language that they use in the contract. אנא אוקים ואגר ואזרע ואחצור
ואעמר ואדוש ואדרי ואוקים כרי קמך. ana okim ve'agar ve'ezra ve'echtzor ve'amar
ve'adush ve'adrei ve'okim kari kamach. I will stand, plow, sow, cut, bind,
thresh, winnow, and set up a stack.
ואת תיתי ותיטול פלגא ve'at teitei vetitol palga you'll come and you'll
take your half. ואנא בעמלי ובנפקות ידי פלגא ve'ana be'amli uvenafkut yadai
palga and I, through the work and the- the money I'd put
out, I'll take the half that- that is owed me. וכמה כדי
להעמיד בה כרי? vekamah kedei le'amid bah kari? They ask: still, what
is this to set up a stack? What is this amount of
wheat? אמר רבי יוסי ברבי חנינא כדי שתעמוד בה רחת amar Rabbi
Yose b'Rabbi Chanina kedei sheta'amod bah rachat that you could stand up
the pitchfork in it.
Lost my place. There it is.
איבעיא להו. ibaia lehu. Okay, we said that it's enough to put
up the- to put it- stick the pitchfork in it, the pitchfork
will stand up. רחת היוצאת מהאי גיסא למהאי גיסא מאי? rachat hayotzet
mehai gisa lehai gisa mai? What if it's coming out at either
point? What if it's like- it'll stand up but you can still
see it? You can still see the forks. תא שמע אמר רבי
אבהו לדידי מפרשא לי מיניה דרבי יוסי ברבי חנינא ta shema amar
Rabbi Abahu ledidi mifarsha li minei d'Rabbi Yose b'Rabbi Chanina I heard
an explanation of this from the person who said it.
Says I heard it from רבי יוסי ברבי חנינא Rabbi Yose b'Rabbi
Chanina himself that what he said: כל שאין כונס שלו רואה פני
החמה. kol she'ein kones shelo roeh pnei hachamah. You have to- it
has to be totally covered by the wheat when you stick it
into it. תוספות Tosafot here quoted different- quoted a
different- a כונס kones is- it's the part with the tines. A
pitchfork, it has a- it's a long stick with the tines at
either end to throw the wheat up in the air so that
for זורה, zoreh, breeze resets that the wheat will come out from
the chaff in the wind.
רבינו חננאל Rabbeinu Chananel has it differently.
רבינו חננאל Rabbeinu Chananel גריס garis in the תוספות מהאי גיסא ומהאי
גיסא mehai gisa umehai gisa פירוש כדי להעמיד צד הרחת של מטה
שזה אין
צריך תבואה כל כך שתעמוד עומד ואינו נופל או מהאי גיסא. perush
kedei le'amid tzad harachat shel matah shezeh ein tzarich tevuah kol kach
sheta'amod omed ve'eino nofel o mehai gisa. Which it's- it's not questioning
which- to have some of it outside of the wheat, but which
side? Is it the side with the tines or is it the
side with- the side that you hold? שמא של אינו רחת שצריך
תבואה הרבה. shama shel eino rachat shetzarich tevuah harbeh. So do I
need- is this really asking... It's still asking how much do I
need is it big or small? But is it it's a much
bigger difference between that I stick the pitchfork in and it's totally
covered or I stick a pitchfork in at the fork end, which
stands up more easily, or I stick the pitchfork in at the
butt end, and it takes a lot more wheat packed together to
keep that standing up.
At the end of the day,
it's כל שאין קניסו לא רואה פני החמה דהיינו צד הרחב שיש
בו בית קיבול. kol she'ein koniso lo ro'eh pnei hachama d'hainu tzad
harachav she'yesh bo beit kibul. There probably was. There probably was. Or
for each area there probably was, because you probably didn't have that
many blacksmiths who were working who were making these things.
It's at the end of the day he concludes רבינו חננאל Rabbeinu
Chananel that it's the pitchfork that's the fork side,
because it talks about the קניס konais in the end.
Okay.
איתמר לוי אמר שלש סאה דבי רבי ינאי אמרי
סאתים. itmar Levi amar shalosh se'ah d'vei Rabbi Yannai amri sa'atayim. How
much is this? They're saying. לוי Levi says it's three סאה se'ah.
and דבי רבי ינאי d'vei Rabbi Yannai in the בית מדרש Beit
Midrash of רבי ינאי Rabbi Yannai they say it's two
סאה. se'ah. אמר ריש לקיש סאתים שאמרו חוץ מן ההוצאה amar Reish
Lakish sa'atayim she'amru chutz min hahotza'ah that that's actually taking that's the
net, that it's after we take out what I had to spend
to make it, this is the סאתים, sa'atayim, which is the amount
that it has to produce in order for me to be required
on my contract of קבלנות to work the field even though it
wasn't producing well. They're also תרומות ומעשרות? Trumot uMaasrot?
Because I have to take out you know. That I don't know
whether that's included in הוצאה. hotza'ah. Probably not because that would be
no, that would be the same on either side. That everybody has
to take out and so I would assume
not.
Okay.
We just heard רבי ינאי Rabbi Yannai say something and apparently the
way the next few things work is a bunch of תנן התם.
Tnan Hatams. One of them an אגור Agur says תנו רבנן Tanu
Rabbanan but it shouldn't be, it should be תנן התם, Tnan Hatam,
we'll come to it in a minute.
And the thing to keep in mind here is why are these
happening, why are we bringing these? And I'll say one version I
read of why are we bringing all these
תנן התם Tnan Hatams in a moment, or one explanation of what
all these tell us, that we're bringing all these תנן התם, Tnan
Hatams, which comes with רבי ינאי Rabbi Yannai at the
end all together here.
תנן התם פריצי זיתים והענבים בית שמאי מטמאין ובית הלל מטהרין. Tnan
Hatam paritzey zeitim veha'anavim Beit Shammai metamin veBeit Hillel metaharin. By the
way all the משניות mishnayot are from טהרות Taharot so we're going
to deal with טהרות Taharot for a moment.
Sort of bad olives or grapes. בית שמאי Beit Shammai say that
they are מקבל טומאה mekabbel tum'ah that they get impurity and בית
הלל Beit Hillel say they don't. ומאי פריצי זיתים? u'mai paritzey zeitim?
What is these פריצי זיתים? paritzey zeitim? I already said they're bad
olives because I read the end of it. אמר רב הונא רשיעי
זיתים, amar Rav Huna rishay zeitim, evil זיתים, zeitim, which here means
that they're bad זיתים, zeitim, they're bad olives that don't produce a
great deal of oil.
והיכי ידעת דפריץ ללישנא? veheichi yadata d'paritz lehishana? I think in our
idiom this is easier to do, that a פורץ גדר poretz geder
which is a language that comes up in הלכה halacha more, someone
who breaks
fences is it's a negatively valence, somebody who breaks fences is sort
of somebody who does things
that are וישכנו נחש v'yishachnu nachash though improper, yeah.
And so פריצות pritzut is also sort of licentiousness and sort of
this has there are nuances in this word for us which mean
bad, but how do we know that it means
רשע? rasha? Or perhaps they also had those
same valences in the word פריץ, paritz, and simply that they wanted
to show off why they knew it meant
that, not show off but that they had a proof that it
meant that.
אמר רב יוסף מאי קרא? amar Rav Yosef mai kra? On what
source do we know that פריץ paritz means
רשע? rasha? ובני פריצי עמך ינשאו להעמיד חזון ונכשלו. u'vnei paritzey amcha
yinassu le'ha'amid chazon venichshalu. The sons of the פריצים paritzim will try
to set up the vision and they will fail. Implicit in that
is that in their failures as the רשעים. rasha'im. רב נחמן בר
יצחק אמר מהכא, Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak amar meihacha, he had a
different source: הוליד בן פריץ שופך דם, holid ben paritz shofech dam,
he fathers a son פריץ paritz who is a spiller of blood.
This spiller of blood is a רשע rasha and so the פריץ
paritz is also a רשע. rasha. A son who is a פריץ.
paritz. Okay.
That's how we know that פריץ paritz means רשע, rasha, which how
we know we're talking about
bad olives that don't produce a great deal of oil. כמה פריצי
זיתים? kama paritzey zeitim? How much is that now? רבי
אלעזר אמר ארבע קבין לכורא Rabbi Elazar amar arba kabbin lekura that
filling up the olive press only produces four קבין kabbin of oil.
דבי רבי ינאי אמרי d'vei Rabbi Yannai amri it produces שתי סאה
shtei se'ah of oil, which is three times as much.
ולא פליגי v'lo pligi says the גמרא Gemara and these are not
actually these aren't actually disagreeing with each other. הא באתרא דמלי כורא
באולולא הא באתרא דמלי תלתא כורין באולולא. ha b'atra de'mali kura b'ulula
ha b'atra de'mali tlata kurin b'ulula. In one place they actually put
three times as many olives into olive press as the other, and
so that's רבי ינאי's Rabbi Yannai place, so it makes sense for
him to give an amount of
olives. תנו
רבנן, Tnu Rabbanan, another this is the thing that should be תנן
התם, Tanan Hatam, another point where רבי ינאי Rabbi Yannai gives an
amount.
אילן שכחו רע, Ilan she'kocho ra, סוכה שכחה רע. socha she'kocha ra.
People, a pure person and an impure person went up on a
tree that or at the or at on branches that had
bad strength, that they were weak,
which sort of means that you put pressure on them and they
show that you're putting pressure on them.
טמא. Tamei. That means that if they're going up together, זב וטהור,
Zav v'Tahor, then the the pure person gets the impurity because they
both sort of they both were on this tree שכחן רע she'kochan
ra and that transfers the impurity, that allows the the impurity to
transfer.
What does it mean אילן שכחו רע? Ilan she'kocho ra? What does
it mean that it has little strength? אמר דבי רבי ינאי, Amar
d'bei Rabbi Yannai, he gives the explanation again, כל שאין בעיקרו לחק
רובע, kol she'ein b'ikaro lachok rova, that the weeds, sorry, not the
weeds, the the roots don't have enough space that you could take
out a רובע, rova, that the the roots of the tree are
very small and so the tree isn't very strong because it doesn't
have enough it doesn't take up enough volume in the ground. היכי
דמי סוכה שכחה רע? Heichi dami socha she'kocha ra? What about the
tops of the trees that are that are weak? אמר ריש לקיש,
Amar Reish Lakish, yeah. What's the connection between the כח רע koach
ra and טומאה? tumah? כח רע koach ra allows if you're standing
on if you're on something that has כח רע, koach ra, that
would allow the impurity to transfer. I don't know exactly, but the
point is like we're going up a tree,
רש"י Rashi says זב וטהור שאילן או סוכה כחו רע או סוכה
נפשו לא כחו רע טמא, Zav v'Tahor she'ilan o socha kocho ra
o socha nafsho lo kocho ra tamei, says רש"י Rashi on the
second line. הטהור שכיון שאילן או סוכה כחו רע נכפפת תחתיהן, HaTahor
she'keivan she'ilan o socha kocho ra nichpefet tachteihen, it sort of bends
underneath and וכבד העליון על התחתון ומשוי עליו מכחו של עליון ובין
זב שנשען על טהור ובין טהור שנשען על זב טמא, kaveid ha'elyon
al ha'tachton u'mishaveh alav mikocho shel elyon u'vein zav she'nishaan al tahor
u'vein tahor she'nishaan al zav tamei, that
because one of the branches are connected,
the branches sort of bend and then the טומאה tumah transfers. If
the branches were solid
and we the they would sort of be separated on the tree,
but because the tree is sort of bending under their weight, the
טומאה tumah transfers from the זב zav to the טמא tamei wherever
you happen to be, because it sort of it sort of connects
the two of them because it's נכפף, nichpaf, נכפפת. nichpefet.
Okay. שאין בעיקרו לחק רובע היכי דמי סוכה שכחה רע? She'ein b'ikaro
lachok rova heichi dami socha she'kocha ra?
The upper branches? What does it mean for them to have little
strength? אמר ריש לקיש, Amar Reish Lakish, כל שנחפסת בחזיונה. kol she'nechpeset
b'chezyonah.
It's רש"י Rashi explains that that means that if you take it
around your hand, you you cover it completely. So this sort of
gives us an idea of in real life what sort of branches
we're talking about. If the branches if you put your entire hand
around it and you can cover it with your hand, that's a
very that's like almost a twig. You're dealing with a very small
branch which is bent under you and so your weight sort of
allows your weight bends it and that allows the טומאה tumah to
transfer. But if you're dealing with this big solid branch that you
can't get your hand around,
then that separates you two on the tree and so your טומאה
tumah doesn't transfer because you're not leaning on one another, so to
speak.
Okay, and we have a third point. תנן התם המהלך בבית הפרס
על גבי אבנים שיכול להסיט. Tnan hatam ha'mahalech b'beit hapras al gabei
avanim she'yachol l'hasit.
It's another טומאה tumah question. We're in a בית הפרס, beit hapras,
which is a place where
שדה שנחרש בה קבר. sadei she'nichrash ba kever. It's somewhere where there
is a קבר kever somewhere in the field. חשו לעצם כשעורה. Chashu
l'etzem k'se'orah. They were concerned about the minimum there being a minimum
amount of bone anywhere, which would be מטמא metamei other people with
טומאת מת. tumat meit. So the minimum amount of bone gives the
highest level of impurity שמטמא במגע ובמשא. she'metamei b'maga u'v'masa. It gives
the highest level of impurity even by touching or by carrying it,
but not by אוהל, ohel, not by overhang. היו שם אבנים שאין
תקועות וקבועות בארץ ואם נסטות
נסטות מחמת העובר עליהן ועצם כשעורה נישא מכחו או רחו
מי שרוצה לאכול טהרות. Hayu sham avanim she'ein tkuot u'kvuot ba'aretz v'im
nistot nistot machmat ha'over aleihen v'etzem k'se'orah nisa mikocho o racho
mi she'rotzeh l'echol tahorot. So that's the next thing. So the point
is is we're going through this field that has somewhere in it
a קבר, kever, and we're worried that anywhere in the field there
might be a little bit of bone and if I knock something
in the field that moves, then I will have that is משא.
masa. That's moving it. That's carrying it. And so if I'm moving
along in the field and I knock a rock, that gives me
the טומאה tumah of the בית הפרס, beit hapras, which is a
דרבנן derabbanan level of of impurity.
On the other hand, if I sort of have a path
And so then we deal with the issue here of the more
difficult case: what if I'm riding on something else? If I'm riding
on something else and it has כחו רע kocho ra again, this
sort of lower level of strength, and that allows the טומאה tumah
to transfer in a בית הפרס Beis ha-Pras unlike when it's just
walking on the ground and the stones move underneath its feet. So,
של מהלכת בבית הפרס על גבי אבנים שיכול להסיט Shel mehaleches be-veit
ha-pras al gabei avanim she-yachol le-hasit that
we're walking on a בית הפרס Beis ha-Pras in this sort of
field with a grave somewhere in it, and it has in it
the stones that move when I kick them, על האדם ועל הבהמה
שכהן רע טמא al ha-adam ve-al ha-beheimah she-kochan ra tamei if I'm
riding on a person or an animal that are weak, then the
טומאה tumah transfers to the person riding. היכי דמי אדם שכהו רע?
Heichi dami adam she-koho ra? אמר ריש לקיש כל שרכובו בארכובותיו נוקשות.
Amar Reish Lakish kol she-rchuvov be-arkuvotav nokshot. Reish
Lakish explains with regard to a person that the knees of the
person walking shake because of the weight of the person he's carrying.
היכי דמי בהמה שכהה רע? Heichi dami behemah she-kohah ra? What does
it mean that the animal is weak? אמרי דבי רבי ינאי כל
שאוכמה מטילה גללים Amrei de-vei Rabbi Yannai kol she-ochma matila gelalim that
the animal because it's so much pressure on the animal that it
leaves droppings while it's being ridden, that's an animal that שכהה רע.
she-kohah ra. That's a weak animal which allows the דרבנן d'Rabbanan טומאה
tumah to transfer.
Okay. The final thing about דבי רבי ינאי, De-vei Rabbi Yannai, אמרי
דבי רבי ינאי לתפלה ולתפילין ארבעה קבין. Amrei de-vei Rabbi Yannai litfillah
u-litfillin arba'ah kabin. He just says the thing. With regard to prayer
and wearing תפילין, tefillin, ארבעה קבין. arba'ah kabin. Great. Totally clear. Which
is why the גמרא Gemara has to go on and explain it
because in fact it's not clear at all.
לתפלה מאי היא? Litfillah mai hi? What are we talking about with
תפלה? tefillah? דתניא הנושא משאוי על כתיפו והגיע זמן תפלה. De-tanya ha-nosei
masoi al kseifo ve-higi'a zeman tefillah. If I'm carrying something on my
shoulders and the time comes for תפלה, tefillah, פחות מארבעה קבין pachos
me-arba'ah kabin if it's less than that amount, משפילו לאחוריו ומתפלל mashpilo
le-achorav u-mispallel
I can throw it over my back like a sack and I
דאבן daven that way. So I can have if I have a
backpack that's less than ארבעה קבין, arba'ah kabin,
a קב kab is about two or three liters, so an eight
liter bag or it's filled with eight liters, then I can have
a small bag on my back while I דאבן. daven.
But ארבעה קבין arba'ah kabin or more than that, ארבעה קבין או
יותר, arba'ah kabin o yoser,
מניח על גבי קרקע ומתפלל manich al gabei karka u-mispallel then you
have to put it on the ground. לתפילין מאי היא? Litfillin mai
hi? What are we talking about when we say תפילין tefillin ארבעה
קבין? arba'ah kabin? דתניא היה
נושא משאוי על ראשו ותפילין בראשו. De-tanya haya nosei masoi al rosho
ve-tefillin be-rosho. If I'm carrying something on my head and תפילין tefillin
are on my head because I wear my תפילין tefillin all day.
אם היו תפילין רוצצות Im hayu tefillin rotzetzos if it's squeezing and
causing the תפילין tefillin to be misshapen,
אסור—that's assur not allowed. ואם לאו מותר Ve-im lav muttar but if
it's not causing the תפילין tefillin to be misshapen, that's allowed. באיזה
משאוי אמרו? Be-eizeh masoi amru? ובמשאוי של ארבעה קבין. U-masoi shel arba'ah
kabin.
That this amount that we're talking about is one that takes up
ארבעה קבין. arba'ah kabin. תניא רבי חייא המוציא זבל על ראשו ותפילין
בראשו. Tanya Rabbi Chiyya ha-motzi zevel al rosho ve-tefillin be-rosho. If
I'm taking out זבל zevel on my head and תפילין tefillin are
on my head, הרי זה לא יסלקם לצדדים ולא יקשרם במתניו. harei
zeh lo yesalkem le-tzadadim ve-lo yiksharem be-mosnav.
I shouldn't put it in the side away from מקום תפילין. mekom
tefillin. I shouldn't put... the מקום תפילין mekom tefillin is only on
the center of the head so I shouldn't move them to the
side of my head so that they're out of the way of
the זבל zevel on my head, they're out of the way of
the manure that I'm carrying, but they're not in the proper place
and I'm not really wearing תפילין. tefillin. And I also shouldn't tie
them on my loins, I shouldn't tie them somewhere else irregular on
my body so that I'm still carrying them around but they're not
in the proper place, מפני שהוא נוהג בהן מנהג בזיון mipnei she-hu
noheg bahem minhag bizayon because that's sort of improper with regard to
תפילין tefillin to put them in the wrong place. אבל קושרן על
זרועו במקום תפילין. Aval kosheran al zero'o bi-mekom tefillin. Rather I should
put them on my arm in the place where I wear my
arm תפילין. tefillin.
I should carry my head תפילין tefillin in the place of my
arm תפילין tefillin
because that's not מנהג בזיון, minhag bizayon, that's sort of not improper
with regard to
תפילין. tefillin. משום דבי רבי שילא אמרו אפילו מטפחת שלהן אסור להניח
על הראש שיש בו תפילין. Mi-shum de-vei Rabbi Sheila amru afilu mitpachas
she-lahen assur le-hani'ach al ha-rosh she-yesh bo tefillin. We have a different
opinion from דבי רבי שילא De-vei Rabbi Sheila about how much I
can put on my head
when I have תפילין tefillin on. And he says even the wrapping
of the תפילין, tefillin, it's not a case, it's not a תיק,
tik, it's a wrapping, it's a piece of fabric. I can't even
put that piece of fabric on my head while I have the
תפילין tefillin on my head. וכמה אמר אביי אפילו ריבעא דריבעא דפומבדיתא?
Ve-kamah amar Abaye afilu riva de-riva de-Pumbedisa? אמר אביי Amar Abaye even
a sixteenth of a קב kab or לוג log from פומבדיתא, Pumbedisa,
which is a very, very, very small amount says רש״י. Rashi. Okay.
So we just went through a whole סוגיא sugya of all the
דבי רבי ינאיs De-vei Rabbi Yannai and then we had דבי רבי
שילא De-vei Rabbi Sheila to give a different opinion on דבי רבי
ינאי. De-vei Rabbi Yannai. What are we dealing with with all these
תנן התםs? tenan hasam
As we pointed out, all of these we're dealing with are טהרה
tahara סוגיאס sugyas and the גמרא Gemara or the בבלי Bavli doesn't
really have מסכתות massekhtot that deal with טהרות taharot סוגיאס, sugyas, but
there are טהרות taharot מסכתות massekhtot on טהרות. taharot. There
is a whole סדר seder that deals with the laws of טומאה
וטהרה tumah ve-taharah and there isn't גמרא Gemara, on it except for
מסכת נדה. Massekhet Niddah. And so these intricate rules aren't really dealt
with in the way that the other rules are dealt with throughout
their own מסכת. massekhet.
That's not to say that the אמוראים Amoraim in בבל Bavel didn't
know them. They did know them, but it's likely according to most
things that only ארבעה סדרים, arba'ah sedarim, the four סדרים sedarim on
which we have גמרא, Gemara were really properly studied in בבל Bavel
and the other ones were sort of אגב אורחא agav orcha that
when they came up they would be looked at, they would be
dealt with and everybody likely knew them by heart in the משנה,
Mishna but they didn't have sort of a set סדר seder in
them as they did with נשים Nashim and נזיקין Nezikin and מועד
Moed and קדשים. Kodashim. Why they studied קדשים Kodashim I can't tell
you.
However we see here with these תנן התם tenan hatams what רש״י
Rashi explains that they're all brought in order here משום סופם mishum
sofam
that each one has an explanation על פי דבי רבי ינאי al
pi de-be Rabbi Yannai of what this שיעור is. We're talking about
we give an amount of something and then we sort of have
to translate that amount into the later measurements. And each one of
these משניות mishnayot has sort of transmitted with it from the school
of רבי ינאי Rabbi Yannai an explanation of what that measurement is
or why that measurement is that way.
David Rozenthal sees this as evidence of sort of that because they're
brought here in this way there's evidence of a תלמוד כאילו Talmud
ke-ilu that there was sort of
there were more formal סוגיות sugyot developed around the משניות mishnayot from
טהרות Taharot and we see them here, we see the early edited
versions of these brought here in this sort of אגב אורחא agav
orcha way that אגב אורחא agav orcha we're talking about דבי רבי
ינאי de-be Rabbi Yannai and sometimes the גמרא Gemara when the מסדרי
הגמרא mesadre ha-Gemara according to רש״י Rashi had to put things in
order, one of the ways in which they did that and were
מצמידותן למשניות, matzmidotan le-mishnayot, they sort of put they הצמידו. hitzmidu. They
attached,
they juxtapose them to משניות, mishnayot, sometimes things that were not particularly
relevant to משנה Mishna came along with them. In this case it's
because each one has the explanation of רבי ינאי, Rabbi Yannai, but
we see here in these that these came from elsewhere that there
was a תלמוד Talmud on the משניות mishnayot from סדר טהרות Seder
Taharot which came into the
בבלי, Bavli, the literary בבלי, Bavli,
in this connected fashion. The other way of putting it is that
it is not so much that there were separate תלמודים Talmuds on
each of the משניות mishnayot in the oral sense and then each
of them and then they were brought in in this literary
fashion that each one as דבי רבי ינאי de-be Rabbi Yannai and
דבי רבי ינאי de-be Rabbi Yannai together. It might simply be that
the דבי רבי ינאי de-be Rabbi Yannai traditions were transmitted together.
That's why they're brought all together because they were already a set.
And so this isn't evidence for סדר טהרות, Seder Taharot, but David
Rozenthal knows better than I.
Okay.
Remember back in the משנה mishna we sort of we had a
מחלוקת machloket about the amount that the field has to produce in
order for a קבלן kablan to be חייב chayav in working the
field.
The תנא קמא Tanna Kamma says אם יש בה כדי להעמיד כרי,
im yesh bah kedei le-ha'amid keri, if it has enough to set
up a stack which we said was either סאתים se'atayim or three
סאה. se'ah
And רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says no, no, no, no, no, it's
אם יש בה כדי נפילה. im yesh bah kedei nefilah.
It need it needs to produce enough that it could seed the
next year. If it's not even making enough to seed the field
the next year then you don't have to work it.
So the גמרא asks back on עמוד ב׳, amud bet, וכמה כדי
נפילה? ve-kamah kedei nefilah? What does it mean that it has to
be able to seed next year?
אמר רבי אמי אמר רבי יוחנן, amar Rabbi Ami amar Rabbi Yochanan,
ארבעה סאים לכור. arba'ah se'im le-khor. The הגהות הב״ח Hagahot ha-Bach says
it's really ארבעה קבים לכור, arba'ah kabbim le-khor,
that it produces four קב kav for a כור. khor. כור khor
רש״י Rashi explains is like 1500 by 50 אמה. amah. Those are
very, very long tracts of field, it's a rather large amount.
And so you need ארבעה קבים arba'ah kabbim of seed to seed
a field that's a כור khor in size. רבי אמי דיליה אמר,
Rabbi Ami dileih amar, שמונה סאים לכור. shmonah se'im le-khor. רבי אמי
Rabbi Ami says for himself, not according to רבי יוחנן, Rabbi Yochanan,
no, you need four קב kav according to that הגהה hagahah of
the ב״ח Bach for a כור khor of field. You need twice
as much seed to seed that much land, 1500 by 50.
אמר ליה ההוא סבא לרב חמא בריה דרבה בר אבוה, amar leih
hahu saba le-Rav Chama bereih de-Rabbah bar Avuha, אסברא לך. asbera lakh.
I'm going to explain to you why these guys said different things.
בשני דרבי יוחנן הויא שמנה ארעא. bishne de-Rabbi Yochanan hava shemena ar'a.
In רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan's days the land was good. בשני דרבי
אמי הויא כחשה ארעא. bishne de-Rabbi Ami hava kachsha ar'a. And the
land of and in the time of רבי אמי Rabbi Ami the
land was bad. It was a little, it was weaker, and so
you needed twice as much feed. Okay. תנן התם, Tnan hatam, we
see again, הרוח שפיזרה את העומרין, Haruach shepizra et ha'omrin, אומדין, omdin,
אומדין אותה כמה לקט היא ראויה לעשות omdin otah kama leket hi
re'uyah la'asot ונותן לעניים. v'noten l'aniyim.
Okay,
so we lost, we had sheaves of wheat that we sort of
packed together, and the wind came and we lost all of it.
We sort of estimate how much the field would have made,
and we give that in לקט leket to poor people. רבן שמעון
בן גמליאל אומר, Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel omer, נותן לעניים כדי נפילה.
noten l'aniyim k'dei nefilah. No, we don't give them an estimated amount.
We give them the amount that it would take to seed the
field. וכמה כדי נפילה? V'kamah k'dei nefilah? And we ask, okay, so
how much does it take to seed a field? כי אתא רב
דימי אמר רבי אלעזר ואיתימא רבי יוחנן, ארבעה קבין לכור. Ki ata
Rav Dimi amar Rabbi Elazar v'itayma Rabbi Yochanan arba'ah kabin l'kor.
Rav Dimi says either in the name of Rabbi Elazar or in
the name of Rabbi Yochanan, ארבעה קבין לכור. arba'ah kabin l'kor. It
takes four, it takes four קבין. kabin. This is why the הגר״א
Gra
changed the text earlier on, because here it says ארבעה קבין arba'ah
kabin and there it says ארבעה סאה, arba'ah se'ah, and we can't
have such wildly different amounts of seed. So obviously this one makes
sense according to him. Why did he change the first one? He
changed the first one because apparently it makes more...
never mind.
Doesn't matter. I'm not sure why he changed one and not the
other. Perhaps he knew more about, he knew more in זרעים Zraim
about how much a קב kab and a סאה se'ah is than
I do. I believe a סאה se'ah is like four times as
much as a קב. kab. I'm not sure about that. Wait.
Three times as much.
A סאה is three times as much. So this is why all
those סוגיות דצערה sugyot d'tzara as it were, the Babylonian סוגיות דצערה
sugyot d'tzara were placed here? Because... no, this is a separate סוגיה
sugyah entirely. But what I was going to ask was because of
the motif of something is strong, something is weak. כוחא... kocha... כוחא
חלשא, kocha chalasha,
right? In other words כוחא רע. kocha ra. In other words, there's
a motif that's running through here. There's enough seed, there's not enough
seed. The olives are bad, the olives are good. In other words,
there's a... that's a much better explanation of why this is happening
than simply משום סיפא mishum seifa that everyone has דבי רבי ינאי
d'bei Rabbi Yannai explaining it.
Yeah, I agree with you. Does that make sense? Makes sense to
me. I think it's really
רש״י Rashi consistently throughout ש״ס Shas identifies places where it's... where he
doesn't give it this language, but that there are sort of short
סוגיות sugyot that follow on one another because they have these
recurring motifs of one particular rabbi gives one particular kind of explanation
at the end of each one. And we can all identify those
where that happens, and there are some that are sort of, that
are sort of vaguer than the others and he doesn't say it
and we need to notice it for ourselves, and there are some
where it's more obvious like here. And he says it explicitly in
עמוד א׳ amud aleph that all of these are the דבי רבי
ינאי d'bei Rabbi Yannai explanations. A better one is why are these
coming, why are these all here? That there's a running theme about
there's sort of...
we're dealing a lot with how much it takes to do this.
What's the, what's the sort of, what is the borderline of the
strength of these things to transfer טומאה, tumah, the strength of these
things to seed the field? Right. There's a natural phenomenon that would
take, like the branches of the tree using so-and-so, what if you
have this kind? What if you have this kind? That seems to
be the motif to me that's aligning. Yeah, I like that better.
This is separate from the first point. The set of the תנן
התם's tnan hatam and the דבי רבי ינאי d'bei Rabbi Yannai are
different.
This is תנן התם tnan hatam of something else, of we're dealing
with כדי נפילה k'dei nefilah and כדי נפילה. k'dei nefilah. This is
about הרוח. haruach. No, this is about זרעים. Zraim. Here we're taking
in the לשון from, here we're taking in פאה. Peah. פאה Peah
had to deal with כדי נפילה k'dei nefilah also, which is what...
when you lose the field, how much do you owe in פאה?
Peah? How much do you owe in לקט leket anyway? And when
we were dealing with כדי נפילה k'dei nefilah we dealt with כדי
נפילה, k'dei nefilah, the amount to re-seed the field in the context
of the field didn't produce when I leased it. Do I still
have to work it? And כדי נפילה k'dei nefilah was according to
רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda the minimum amount necessary that the field produced
in order that I be required to work it nonetheless.
But it's brought here because... this is a different reason that this
משנה mishna is brought here. This משנה mishna. is זרעים, Zraim, which
is the other סדר seder that the אמוראי בבלי Amora'ei Bavli didn't
produce. Here it's not because we have דבי רבי ינאי d'bei Rabbi
Yannai explaining it at the end according to the less nuanced explanation
of why the דבי רבי ינאי d'bei Rabbi Yannai all came. But
here it's because כדי נפילה k'dei nefilah has to be explained in
both sides. And so we had to, we explained them together in
the literary structure of the בבלי. Bavli. וכמה כדי נפילה? V'kamah k'dei
nefilah? כי אתא רב דימי אמר רבי אלעזר ואיתימא רבי יוחנן Ki
ata Rav Dimi amar Rabbi Elazar v'itayma Rabbi Yochanan, ארבעה קבין
לכור. arba'ah kabin l'kor. He says the same thing, that it's ארבעה,
arba'ah, that it's four קבין kabin for a כור kor of the
field. בעי רבי ירמיה: Ba'ei Rabbi Yirmeyah:
לכור זרע או לכור תבואה? L'kor zera o l'kor tevuah? Is this
a כור kor of seed or a כור kor of produce?
I saw an explanation that has this... that has this question make
sense. רבי ירמיה Rabbi Yirmeyah usually doesn't make sense. רבי ירמיה Rabbi
Yirmeyah usually asks questions where the difference is exceedingly fine, so much
so that a normal human being would say it doesn't matter. But
רבי ירמיה Rabbi Yirmeyah is much more clever and asks
annoying questions. Right so
this one the version of this question that makes sense is is
this כור kor *kor* I don't even know how it makes sense.
It doesn't make sense. It's two different volumes that are the same
volume. A liter is it a liter of seed or is it
a liter of wheat? But but a liter of seed is a
lot more, like that leads to a lot more produce than a
liter of produce, right? Like you
have I don't know, let's say a certain I'm going to make
the numbers small so I can if you have thirty seed, right,
five heads of lettuce. Right, but when I give לקט *leket* I
give תבואה *tuah*.
You give what? When I give לקט *leket* when I give this
amount of sort of I when I give the צדקה *tzedakah* certain
amount of צדקה *tzedakah* comes out of the field and I give
it to a poor person, I'm giving wheat.
So you're saying it's obvious of the produce. I think no, they
say the opposite. That it's a כור kor זרע zera *kor zera*
which means that it has to do with the amount of seed
that it takes to put in a field.
I honestly don't understand the question and I've been trying to understand
the question for a day. No no no but they just wanted
to know if it's a כור *kor* of what you're giving or
a כור *kor* of what you're take. Yeah. It's a
רש"י Rashi *Rashi* that says what one size
the smallest of sizes is. It's a כור *kor*. I know. For
כור זרע *kor zera* does it have to produce is it have
to be
the amount that's planted לשדה שזרעו בכור או לשדה שלוקט בכור
תבואה *lishadesh shezaru bakor o lishadesh sheloket bakor tevuah*. Is it a
very big is it a very big field that requires a כור
*kor* that requires the כור *kor* of seed to put it in
or is it a seed that produces a כור *kor* of תבואה
*tevuah*? אם תמצא לומר *im titzel lomar* כור זרע *kor zera* למפולת
יד או למפולת שוורים *lmapolet yad o lmapolet shevarim*? When we're talking
about seed, is this seed this is the question they don't answer.
So maybe the first question
does make sense and I'm assuming that it doesn't make sense.
The annoying question is are we talking which actually makes more sense
to me
are we talking about hand seeding or seeding by automatically through animals
going around? So I have to say that the second question makes
much more sense to me because I'm pretty sure that a מפולת
יד *mapolet yad* is a appreciable difference. If I'm going around and
seeding by hand and I'm sort of not quite seeding automatically, I
could be using a significantly less seed to seed my field than
if I'm going around and using an automatic thing. That when I'm
dealing with machines that sort of can only deal with the holder
in a certain way and they have to only deal with it
in a certain way and they deal with it automatically, then there's
no intelligence in the machine to say oh here I only need
a little bit and here I need more. It's going to give
out the same amount no matter what. And that's usually I think
it's going to end up being slightly more.
The first question apparently hand sowing or with an ox. Sowing with
an ox uses more seed. Yeah and by
hand. Which so this question makes sense, but it's a very fine
distinction. They don't end up answering the question. And if you're sitting
on a planter there seeding or you're walking behind with a prod
or whatever the thing is, it's going automatically. And one would drop
more seed. It's a spinner or the John Deere. The ox would
drop more seed. The John Ox. The ox would go about and
the ox sort of has some sort of spinning thing like the
way that they do when they salt the streets. They have a
thing that goes about and it has a big pile of salt
and it goes and it salts and it like spreads out a
ton of salt on the streets. Obviously the streets need more salt,
actually they don't, but they need less salt because bad for the
salt. The point is that we can see this in real life.
They put out salt automatically. If we're going around and we're salting
our driveways, we're going to put somewhat less, because we see where
it needs it and the truck doesn't see where it needs it.
Good. תא שמע *ta shma*. תא שמע *ta shma*. We have an
answer to the question of whether we put in whether it's שזרעו
בכור *shezaru bakor* כור זרע *kor
zera*. I just don't understand.
Okay.
They give an answer. תא שמע *ta shma*. דכי אתא רבין אמר
רבי אבא בר אלעזר ואמרי לה רבי יוחנן *deki ata Ravin amar
Rabbi Abba bar Elazar ve'amri lah Rabbi Yochanan*. The answer they give
from the same source ארבעה קבין לכור זרע *arba kabin lekor zera*.
That a field that requires a כור *kor* of זרע *zera* to
produce gives out ארבעה קבין *arba kabin*. That's what כדי נפילה *kedei
nefilah* means. ועדיין תיבעי לך מפולת יד או מפולת שוורים *ve'adayan tiba'i
lach mapolet yad o mapolet shevarim* and they still the question תיקו
*teiku*. They let it stand. They do not know whether this is
nine-tenths of a liter or one liter, something like that. רש"י *Rashi*
what's your explanation for the story? Yes שוורים *shevarim*. כור זרע לשדה
שזרעו בכור או לשדה שלוקט בכור תבואה *kor zera lishadesh shezaru bakor
o lishadesh sheloket bakor tevuah*
which is a very small field but you still give him כדי
נפילה *kedei nefilah*. אה כדי נפילה *ah kedei nefilah* is the amount
of כדי נפילה *kedei nefilah* is the amount of seed to seed
that field.
Ah, so it's a that's actually significant, that's what he had this
at once. A כור זרע is a significant amount because it's the
זרע that it takes to seed an entire כור field and the
כור תבואה kor tvua is a field that produces a כור of
produce, which is a much smaller field.
The next רש''י on me, the next רש''י says how I said
that the שברים shevarim are going to make more. Okay. We can
do, we can't do. Okay, we're going to start pick up tomorrow
with the משנה.